<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Compilers | yagooar locus]]></title>
  <link href="http://yagooar.github.io/blog/categories/compilers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yagooar.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-14T17:33:27+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://yagooar.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mati Sójka]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Is a Compiler?]]></title>
    <link href="http://yagooar.github.io/b/what-is-a-compiler/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T22:43:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://yagooar.github.io/b/what-is-a-compiler</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Much of my work has come from being lazy.</p><footer><strong>John Backus</strong> <cite>Creator of Fortran</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<h3>A compiler is a translator.</h3>

<p>Simple, huh? Indeed, the concept behind a compiler is pretty straight forward.
We have a program written in one language, and ask our hero &ndash; The Compiler &ndash;
to translate it into another language.</p>

<p>But when it comes to the very process of translating, things get a little bit
involved. A compiler takes care of a lot of different processes that put
together allow to create a new version of a program. The most common use case
is translating a high-level programming language into a low-level one
(hint: assembly). Sometimes the translation is done straight into machine or
byte code.</p>

<h3>Why do we even need code compilation?</h3>

<p>In order to answer that question, we have to go back in history. Back in the
50s, programming was quite different than now. Resources were limited and
 software costs passed those of hardware. Scientists and engineers began to
worry about reducing programmers' productivity in order to cut those huge costs.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>Soon enough, Backus realized that what would greatly improve speed of execution
and reduce memory consumption would be a program that would <em>translate</em> a
a complete program written in a high-level language into machine code, and than
execute the translated program. This is how Fortran and its compiler were
created.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s interesting is, that even today, programming languages that are compiled
run faster and consume less memory than the interpreted ones, so it still holds
true after 60 years of computer science.</p>

<h3>The benefits of compilers are immense</h3>

<p>Compilers not only allow to program in a more user-friendly language, but also
allow to abstract machine differences. We write the code once, and compilers
translate our code into different machine languages and dialects.</p>

<p>But after finding out all those benefits, we still don&rsquo;t actually know how
compilers do their job. Let&rsquo;s change that.</p>

<h3>The compilation process</h3>

<p>Take a look at the following graph:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/compiler.svg"></p>

<p>What we see here is that first of all, the compiler takes care of the
translation of the source code into a target code. After that, we just take the
<em>target code</em>, also called <em>target program</em>, and run it by providing it some
data. In this scenario, the compiler&rsquo;s work actually finishes after the first
step. So let&rsquo;s try to find out how this <em>Compiler</em> box actually works.</p>

<h3>How compilation works</h3>

<p>Explaining the whole process of compilation is definitely too much for one
single blog post, so let&rsquo;s just get a quick overview of the different steps:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Lexical Analysis</strong>: the source code is read and converted into meaningful
units, called <em>lexemes</em>. Those are then converted into <em>tokens</em>.</li>
<li><strong>Syntax Analysis</strong> or <strong>Parsing</strong>: the tokens are parsed into an intermediate
representation, called <em>syntax tree</em>.</li>
<li><strong>Semantic Analysis</strong>: The <em>syntax tree</em> is used to check the semantic
consistency with the language grammar.</li>
<li><strong>Intermediate Code Generation</strong>: the compiler creates a low-level
representation of the program. It is often built for an abstract machine,
but can easily be translated into real machine code.</li>
<li><strong>Code Optimization</strong>: optimization rules are applied to the intermediate
code, in order to increase speed of execution or minimize memory or resource
consumption. This is one of the most complex and unique parts of the
compilation process.</li>
<li><strong>Code Generation</strong>: the intermediate, optimized code is finally translated
into the target language.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>We have seen that a compiler is actually a translator, which makes programmers
more productive and happy and the programs more universal and portable.
To accomplish this task, there are some required steps like analyzing the input
and generating the new output.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
